<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><unesco><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_1127.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Muskauer Park / Park Mukakowski]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>A landscaped park of 559.9 ha astride the Neisse River and the border between Poland and Germany, it was created by Prince Hermann von Puckler-Muskau from 1815 to 1844. Blending seamlessly with the surrounding farmed landscape, the park pioneered new approaches to landscape design and influenced the development of landscape architecture in Europe and America. Designed as a &lsquo;painting with plants&rsquo;, it did not seek to evoke classical landscapes, paradise, or some lost perfection, instead using local plants to enhance the inherent qualities of the existing landscape. This integrated landscape extends into the town of Muskau with green passages that formed urban parks framing areas for development. The town thus became a design component in a utopian landscape. The site also features a reconstructed castle, bridges and an arboretum.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_1314.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[The Wadden Sea]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>The Wadden Sea comprises the Dutch Wadden Sea Conservation Area and the German Wadden Sea National Parks of Lower Saxony and Schleswig-Holstein. It is a large temperate, relatively flat coastal wetland environment, formed by the intricate interactions between physical and biological factors that have given rise to a multitude of transitional habitats with tidal channels, sandy shoals, sea-grass meadows, mussel beds, sandbars, mudflats, salt marshes, estuaries, beaches and dunes. The inscribed site represents over 66% of the whole Wadden Sea and is home to numerous plant and animal species, including marine mammals such as the harbour seal, grey seal and harbour porpoise. It is also a breeding and wintering area for up to 12 millions birds per annum and it supports more than 10 percent of 29 species. The site is one of the last remaining natural, large-scale, intertidal ecosystems where natural processes continue to function largely undisturbed.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_3.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Aachen Cathedral ]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[State of North Rhine-Westphalia (Nordrhein-Westfalen)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>Construction of this palatine chapel, with its octagonal basilica and cupola, began c. 790&ndash;800 under the Emperor Charlemagne. Originally inspired by the churches of the Eastern part of the Holy Roman Empire, it was splendidly enlarged in the Middle Ages.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_168.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Speyer Cathedral]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[State of Rhineland-Palatinate (Rheinland-Pfalz)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>Speyer Cathedral, a basilica with four towers and two domes, was founded by Conrad II in 1030 and remodelled at the end of the 11th century. It is one of the most important Romanesque monuments from the time of the Holy Roman Empire. The cathedral was the burial place of the German emperors for almost 300 years.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_288.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Castles of Augustusburg and Falkenlust at Brühl]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[State of North Rhine-Westphalia (Nordrhein-Westfalen)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>Set in an idyllic garden landscape, Augustusburg Castle (the sumptuous residence of the prince-archbishops of Cologne) and the Falkenlust hunting lodge (a small rural folly) are among the earliest examples of Rococo architecture in 18th-century Germany.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_367.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Roman Monuments, Cathedral of St Peter and Church of Our Lady in Trier]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[State of Rhineland-Palatinate (Rheinland-Pfalz)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>Trier, which stands on the Moselle River, was a Roman colony from the 1st century AD and then a great trading centre beginning in the next century. It became one of the capitals of the Tetrarchy at the end of the 3rd century, when it was known as the &lsquo;second Rome&rsquo;. The number and quality of the surviving monuments are an outstanding testimony to Roman civilization.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_532.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Palaces and Parks of Potsdam and Berlin]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[States of Brandenburg and Berlin]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>With 500 ha of parks and 150 buildings constructed between 1730 and 1916, Potsdam&rsquo;s complex of palaces and parks forms an artistic whole, whose eclectic nature reinforces its sense of uniqueness. It extends into the district of Berlin-Zehlendorf, with the palaces and parks lining the banks of the River Havel and Lake Glienicke. Voltaire stayed at the Sans-Souci Palace, built under Frederick II between 1745 and 1747.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_534.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Garden Kingdom of Dessau-Wörlitz]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[State of Saxony-Anhalt (Sachsen-Anhalt)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>The Garden Kingdom of Dessau-W&ouml;rlitz is an exceptional example of landscape design and planning of the Age of the Enlightenment, the 18th century. Its diverse components - outstanding buildings, landscaped parks and gardens in the English style, and subtly modified expanses of agricultural land - serve aesthetic, educational, and economic purposes in an exemplary manner.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_535.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Collegiate Church, Castle and Old Town of Quedlinburg]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[State of Saxony-Anhalt (Sachsen-Anhalt)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>Quedlinburg, in the <em>Land</em> of Sachsen-Anhalt, was a capital of the East Franconian German Empire at the time of the Saxonian-Ottonian ruling dynasty. It has been a prosperous trading town since the Middle Ages. The number and high quality of the timber-framed buildings make Quedlinburg an exceptional example of a medieval European town. The Collegiate Church of St Servatius is one of the masterpieces of Romanesque architecture.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_546.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Maulbronn Monastery Complex]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[District of Enz, State of Baden-Württemberg]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>Founded in 1147, the Cistercian Maulbronn Monastery is considered the most complete and best-preserved medieval monastic complex north of the Alps. Surrounded by fortified walls, the main buildings were constructed between the 12th and 16th centuries. The monastery&rsquo;s church, mainly in Transitional Gothic style, had a major influence in the spread of Gothic architecture over much of northern and central Europe. The water-management system at Maulbronn, with its elaborate network of drains, irrigation canals and reservoirs, is of exceptional interest.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_624.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Town of Bamberg]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[District of Upper Franconia]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>From the 10th century onwards, this town became an important link with the Slav peoples, especially those of Poland and Pomerania. During its period of greatest prosperity, from the 12th century onwards, the architecture of Bamberg strongly influenced northern Germany and Hungary. In the late 18th century it was the centre of the Enlightenment in southern Germany, with eminent philosophers and writers such as Hegel and Hoffmann living there.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_687.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Völklingen Ironworks]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[State of Saarland]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>The ironworks, which cover some 6 ha, dominate the city of V&ouml;lklingen. Although they have recently gone out of production, they are the only intact example, in the whole of western Europe and North America, of an integrated ironworks that was built and equipped in the 19th and 20th centuries and has remained intact.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_729.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Bauhaus and its Sites in Weimar and Dessau]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[States of Saxony-Anhalt (Sachsen-Anhalt) and Thuringia (Thüringen)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>Between 1919 and 1933, the Bauhaus School, based first in Weimar and then in Dessau, revolutionized architectural and aesthetic concepts and practices. The buildings put up and decorated by the school&rsquo;s professors (Walter Gropius, Hannes Meyer, Laszlo Moholy-Nagy and Wassily Kandinsky) launched the Modern Movement, which shaped much of the architecture of the 20th century.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_783.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Luther Memorials in Eisleben and Wittenberg]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[States of Saxony-Anhalt (Sachsen-Anhalt) and Thuringia (Thüringen)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>These places in Saxony-Anhalt are all associated with the lives of Martin Luther and his fellow-reformer Melanchthon. They include Melanchthon&rsquo;s house in Wittenberg, the houses in Eisleben where Luther was born in 1483 and died in 1546, his room in Wittenberg, the local church and the castle church where, on 31 October 1517, Luther posted his famous &rsquo;95 Theses&rsquo;, which launched the Reformation and a new era in the religious and political history of the Western world.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_846.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Classical Weimar]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[State of Thuringia (Thüringen)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>In the late 18th and early 19th centuries the small Thuringian town of Weimar witnessed a remarkable cultural flowering, attracting many writers and scholars, notably Goethe and Schiller. This development is reflected in the high quality of many of the buildings and of the parks in the surrounding area.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_896.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Museumsinsel (Museum Island), Berlin]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[Berlin (city-state)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>The museum as a social phenomenon owes its origins to the Age of Enlightenment in the 18th century. The five museums on the Museumsinsel in Berlin, built between 1824 and 1930, are the realization of a visionary project and show the evolution of approaches to museum design over the course of the 20th century. Each museum was designed so as to establish an organic connection with the art it houses. The importance of the museum&rsquo;s collections &ndash; which trace the development of civilizations throughout the ages &ndash; is enhanced by the urban and architectural quality of the buildings.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_897.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Wartburg Castle]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[Eisenach, State of Thuringia (Thüringen)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>Wartburg Castle blends superbly into its forest surroundings and is in many ways &rsquo;the ideal castle&rsquo;. Although it has retained some original sections from the feudal period, the form it acquired during the 19th-century reconstitution gives a good idea of what this fortress might have been at the height of its military and seigneurial power. It was during his exile at Wartburg Castle that Martin Luther translated the New Testament into German.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_974.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Monastic Island of Reichenau]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[District of Freiburg, State of Baden-Württemberg]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>The island of Reichenau on Lake Constance preserves the traces of the Benedictine monastery, founded in 724, which exercised remarkable spiritual, intellectual and artistic influence. The churches of St Mary and Marcus, St Peter and St Paul, and St George, mainly built between the 9th and 11th centuries, provide a panorama of early medieval monastic architecture in central Europe. Their wall paintings bear witness to impressive artistic activity.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_975.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Zollverein Coal Mine Industrial Complex in Essen]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[State of North Rhine-Westphalia (Nordrhein-Westfalen)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>The Zollverein industrial complex in Land Nordrhein-Westfalen consists of the complete infrastructure of a historical coal-mining site, with some 20th-century buildings of outstanding architectural merit. It constitutes remarkable material evidence of the evolution and decline of an essential industry over the past 150 years.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_1066.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Upper Middle Rhine Valley]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[States of Rhineland-Palatinate (Rheinland-Pfalz) and  Hesse (Hessen)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>The 65km-stretch of the Middle Rhine Valley, with its castles, historic towns and vineyards, graphically illustrates the long history of human involvement with a dramatic and varied natural landscape. It is intimately associated with history and legend and for centuries has exercised a powerful influence on writers, artists and composers.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_1067.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Historic Centres of Stralsund and Wismar]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[State of Mecklenburg-Western Pomerania (Mecklenburg-Vorpommern)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>The medieval towns of Wismar and Stralsund, on the Baltic coast of northern Germany, were major trading centres of the Hanseatic League in the 14th and 15th centuries. In the 17th and 18th centuries they became Swedish administrative and defensive centres for the German territories. They contributed to the development of the characteristic building types and techniques of Brick Gothic in the Baltic region, as exemplified in several important brick cathedrals, the Town Hall of Stralsund, and the series of houses for residential, commercial and crafts use, representing its evolution over several centuries.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_1087.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Town Hall and Roland on the Marketplace of Bremen]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[Bremen (city-state)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>The Town Hall and the statue of Roland on the marketplace of Bremen in north-west Germany are outstanding representations of civic autonomy and sovereignty, as these developed in the Holy Roman Empire in Europe. The old town hall was built in the Gothic style in the early 15th century, after Bremen joined the Hanseatic League. The building was renovated in the so-called Weser Renaissance style in the early 17th century. A new town hall was built next to the old one in the early 20th century as part of an ensemble that survived bombardment during the Second World War. The statue stands 5.5 m tall and dates back to 1404.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_1155.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Old town of Regensburg with Stadtamhof]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[Bavaria]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>Located on the Danube River in Bavaria, this medieval town contains many buildings of exceptional quality that testify to its history as a trading centre and to its influence on the region from the 9th century. A notable number of historic structures span some two millennia and include ancient Roman, Romanesque and Gothic buildings. Regensburg&rsquo;s 11th- to 13th-century architecture &ndash; including the market, city hall and cathedral &ndash; still defines the character of the town marked by tall buildings, dark and narrow lanes, and strong fortifications. The buildings include medieval patrician houses and towers, a large number of churches and monastic ensembles as well as the 12th-century Old Bridge. The town is also remarkable for the vestiges testifing to its rich history as one of the centres of the Holy Roman Empire that turned to Protestantism.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_1239.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Berlin Modernism Housing Estates]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>Berlin Modernism Housing Estates. The property consists of six housing estates that testify to innovative housing policies from 1910 to 1933, especially during the Weimar Republic, when the city of Berlin was particularly progressive socially, politically and culturally. The property is an outstanding example of the building reform movement that contributed to improving housing and living conditions for people with low incomes through novel approaches to town planning, architecture and garden design. The estates also provide exceptional examples of new urban and architectural typologies, featuring fresh design solutions, as well as technical and aesthetic innovations. Bruno Taut, Martin Wagner and Walter Gropius were among the leading architects of these projects which exercised considerable influence on the development of housing around the world.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_623.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Mines of Rammelsberg, Historic Town of Goslar and Upper Harz Water Management  System]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>The Upper Harz mining water management system, which lies south of the Rammelsberg mines and the town of Goslar, has been developed over a period of some 800 years to assist in the process of extracting ore for the production of non-ferrous metals. Its construction was first undertaken in the Middle Ages by Cistercian monks, and it was then developed on a vast scale from the end of the 16th century until the 19th century. It is made up of an extremely complex but perfectly coherent system of artificial ponds, small channels, tunnels and underground drains. It enabled the development of water power for use in mining and metallurgical processes. It is a major site for mining innovation in the western world.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_187.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[St Mary&rsquo;s Cathedral and St Michael&rsquo;s Church at Hildesheim]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[District of Hanover, State of Lower Saxony (Niedersachsen)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>St Michael&rsquo;s Church was built between 1010 and 1020 on a symmetrical plan with two apses that was characteristic of Ottonian Romanesque art in Old Saxony. Its interior, in particular the wooden ceiling and painted stucco-work, its famous bronze doors and the Bernward bronze column, are &ndash; together with the treasures of St Mary&rsquo;s Cathedral &ndash; of exceptional interest as examples of the Romanesque churches of the Holy Roman Empire.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_292.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Cologne Cathedral]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[State of North Rhine-Westphalia (Nordrhein-Westfalen)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>Begun in 1248, the construction of this Gothic masterpiece took place in several stages and was not completed until 1880. Over seven centuries, successive builders were inspired by the same faith and a spirit of absolute fidelity to the original plans. Apart from its exceptional intrinsic value and the artistic masterpieces it contains, Cologne Cathedral testifies to the enduring strength of European Christianity.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_272.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Hanseatic City of Lübeck]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[State of Schleswig-Holstein]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>L&uuml;beck &ndash; the former capital and Queen City of the Hanseatic League &ndash; was founded in the 12th century and prospered until the 16th century as the major trading centre for northern Europe. It has remained a centre for maritime commerce to this day, particularly with the Nordic countries. Despite the damage it suffered during the Second World War, the basic structure of the old city, consisting mainly of 15th- and 16th-century patrician residences, public monuments (the famous Holstentor brick gate), churches and salt storehouses, remains unaltered.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_720.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Messel Pit Fossil Site]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[District of Darmstadt-Dieburg, State of Hesse (Hessen)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>Messel Pit is the richest site in the world for understanding the living environment of the Eocene, between 57 million and 36 million years ago. In particular, it provides unique information about the early stages of the evolution of mammals and includes exceptionally well-preserved mammal fossils, ranging from fully articulated skeletons to the contents of stomachs of animals of this period.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_169.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Würzburg Residence with the Court Gardens and Residence Square]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[District of Lower Franconia, State of Bavaria (Bayern)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>This magnificent Baroque palace &ndash; one of the largest and most beautiful in Germany and surrounded by wonderful gardens &ndash; was created under the patronage of the prince-bishops Lothar Franz and Friedrich Carl von Sch&ouml;nborn. It was built and decorated in the 18th century by an international team of architects, painters (including Tiepolo), sculptors and stucco-workers, led by Balthasar Neumann.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_1368.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Fagus Factory in Alfeld]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>Fagus Factory in Alfeld is a 10-building complex - began around 1910 to the design of Walter Gropius, which is a landmark in the development of modern architecture and industrial design. Serving all stages of manufacture, storage and dispatch of lasts used by the shoe industry, the complex, which is still operational today, is situated in Alfeld an der Leine in Lower Saxony. With its groundbreaking vast expanses of glass panels and functionalist aesthetics, the complex foreshadowed the work of the Bauhaus school and is a landmark in the development of architecture in Europe and North America.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_1379.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Margravial Opera House Bayreuth]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>A masterpiece of Baroque theatre architecture, built between 1745 and 1750, the Opera House is the only entirely preserved example of its type where an audience of 500 can experience Baroque court opera culture and acoustics authentically, as its auditorium retains its original materials, i.e. wood and canvas. Commissioned by Margravine Wilhelmine, wife of Frederick, Margrave of Brandenburg&ndash;Beyreuth, it was designed by the renowned theatre architect Giuseppe Galli Bibiena. As a court opera house in a public space, it foreshadowed the large public theatres of the 19th century. The highly decorated theatre&rsquo;s tiered loge structure of wood with illusionistic painted canvas represents the ephemeral ceremonial architectural tradition that was employed in pageants and celebrations for princely self-representation.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_271.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Pilgrimage Church of Wies]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[Town of Steingaden, District of Weilheim-Schongau, Region of Upper Bavaria, State of Bavaria (Bayern)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>Miraculously preserved in the beautiful setting of an Alpine valley, the Church of Wies (1745&ndash;54), the work of architect Dominikus Zimmermann, is a masterpiece of Bavarian Rococo &ndash; exuberant, colourful and joyful.</p>]]></info></item><item><land>Germany</land><bild>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_515.jpg</bild><platz><![CDATA[Abbey and Altenmünster of Lorsch]]></platz><ort><![CDATA[District of Bergstrasse, State of Hesse (Hessen)]]></ort><info><![CDATA[<p>The abbey, together with its monumental entrance, the famous &rsquo;Torhall&rsquo;, are rare architectural vestiges of the Carolingian era. The sculptures and paintings from this period are still in remarkably good condition.</p>]]></info></item></unesco>